# James Muita Kiboi

E: jaykiboi2018@gmail.com T: +254721418479

# **Professional Summary**

Self- driven, result- oriented Mechanical Engineer with over a decade of experience in the industry. Wide experience with all types of cooling equipment as well as with operational management, building and design techniques, preventative maintenance and electro-mechanical troubleshooting. Ability to learn on the job and implement projects as needed based on the site layout or schematics, the equipment requirements, budget and needs of the client. Strongly focused on quality workmanship to always ensure customer satisfaction.

#### **Skills**

- Extensive knowledge of HVAC controls, operation, diagnostics, and maintenance with solid problem-solving skills.
- Well versed in forecasting and planning with a view to optimal utilization of resources to ensure equipment is always in best working condition.
- Effective at multi-tasking and managing the demands of several projects on an ongoing basis.
- Skilled at managing teams and making sure that all members are on the same page, so tasks are completed in a timely manner.
- Strong commitment and strict adherence to Health, Safety and Environmental standards at the workplace.
- Good communicator; adept at building and maintaining person –person relationships.
- Strong computer skills

# **Supplementary Skills**

#### **Software Development:**

- **Front-End Development:** Proficient in React, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, and Styled-components for building interactive and responsive user interfaces.
- **Back-End Development:** Skilled in Node.js and Express.js for developing server-side logic and APIs.
- **Database Management:** Experienced in MongoDB Atlas for managing and maintaining databases.
- **API Integration:** Capable of integrating RESTful APIs and third-party APIs, including Mpesa Daraja API for secure payment transactions.
- State Management: Proficient in Redux for managing application states efficiently.
- **Version Control:** Experienced in using Git and GitHub for version control and collaboration.
- Portfolio: View my portfolio <u>here</u> to explore my projects and capabilities in software development.

### **Work Experience**

Software Developer: Bidmania Ventures August 2023 – January 2024

# Responsibilities:

- Developing back-end functionality and MongoDB databases for web applications.
- Integrating M-Pesa online payment using Daraja API, enhancing user experience and enabling secure transactions.
- Collaborating with cross-functional teams to deliver user-centric features and ensure high-quality solutions.

Sales Engineer: America Air Filter (A.A.F)/Daikin July 2019 — March 2021

# **Responsibilities:**

- Developing and consolidating the East African Air Filters market across hospitals, pharmaceuticals companies, industries and other sectors.
- Preparing and delivering high impact technical presentations of our product range to prospective clients and also addressing their queries.
- Following up on prospective clients, listening to their feedback and sending technical proposals based on their needs.
- Preparing comprehensive quotations in response to client requirements and handling subsequent paper work.
- Handling after sales services including technical assistance and any concerns by clients regarding our products thereby cementing long term client relationship.
- Representing the company in conferences, seminars and exhibitions while targeting policy and decision makers.
- Arranging for pre-shipment inspection of products at point of manufacture and liaising with shippers to ensure timely delivery of goods to clients

Projects Engineer: Edge Point Engineering Ltd May 2016 — July 2019 Responsibilities:

- Responsible for the business as a whole to include projects and personnel.
- Actively seeking for business leads through calls, attending seminars, exhibitions and networking
- Preparing and filling detailed BOQs of upcoming projects and cost variations in on-going works
- Keeping an eye on costs to ensure projects are completed on budget
- Leading and motivating a team of supervisors and technicians on a day-to-day basis and coordinate their schedules to ensure timely completion of projects.
- Attending meetings with consultants, contractors and clients to evaluate on-going and upcoming projects
- Maintaining up to date compliance documents to ensure strict adherence to building codes
- Advising customers on best practices to ensure energy savings from their HVAC equipment
- Projects commissioning.

Projects Coordinator: Justinair Tech Ltd April 2008 – April 2016 Responsibilities:

- Assisted the Projects manager in designing and evaluation of projects
- Accompanied and/or represented the manager at project evaluation meetings alongside consultants, other contractors and clients.
- Developed excel spreadsheets that automated HVAC load calculations for designing purposes.
- Delivered technical support and training to technicians while out working on client systems so projects could be completed in an effective, timely manner.
- Completed building evaluations and made recommendations to customers on the most effective solutions matching their needs and how to enhance the functionality and efficiency of existing equipment.
- Oversaw the day-to-day activities of a team of technicians while ensuring quality control.
- Coordinating emergency response team in cases of breakdown to ensure clients business is not disrupted.
- Ensuring our company adherence to regulatory codes (NCA, NEMA, and Local Council) by following up timely renewal of certificates and ensuring strict adherence to compliance requirements like OSHA.

- Conduct energy audits to identify areas where efficiency can be improved for lower operational costs and greater environmental comfort.
- Projects commissioning.

#### Project Coordinator; Raerex E.A Ltd (HVAC/R) March 2007 – March 2008

- Involvement in making project proposals
- Project planning
- Preparation of Tender documents/ Bills of Quantities.
- Supervising a team of technicians on a day to day basis and ensuring they are provided with materials and tools to ensure optimal performance.
- Acted as a link between technicians and stores on one side and management on the other ensuring a smooth flow of information and logistics.
- Representing company in project evaluation meetings.
- Ensuring design changes are effected as directed by consultants in a timely manner.
- Diagnosed equipment problems and determined what method should be used to restore functionality.
- Ordered parts and equipment, so resources were always available when a client call came through.
- Worked within a team of 10 technicians and provided support on a day-to-day basis that allowed for client requests to be handled in a timely manner.

# Management Trainee (Dispatch officer); Kenol Kobil Kenya Ltd November 2006 – March 2007

- Receiving orders and processing sales of fuel and lubricants
- Compiling daily sales report
- Scheduling truck drivers on optimal routes for smooth and timely delivery of products to clients
- Attending calibration exercises involving fuel transporters.

# **Education**

#### Bachelor of Technology in Production and Mechanical Engineering Moi University 2006

#### **Publications:**

- The Advantages of Demand Controlled Ventilation (DCV) in HVAC systems.
- Co-combustion as a technique of reducing agglomeration in Fluidised bed combustor.
- Carried out research on increasing Thermal efficiency of the fire tube boiler with a projected 24% cut in fuel costs

#### **Training:**

- Attended Air filtration products and Daikin HVAC manufacturing training in Dubai and India in June 2019
- Sales and Marketing Seminar in Nyali, Mombasa
- Samsung accredited installer certificate after four days training at Samsung service centre Nairobi.
- Attended Trane workshop at New Stanley Hotel, Nairobi.

#### **Hobbies and Interests**

I enjoy travelling to new places, visiting national parks and exploring natural features. Additionally, I like spending time researching on latest technology trends, motoring trends especially on vintage cars rehabilitation, reading everything within range and completing home renovations projects. Finally I love cooking for my family whenever possible as well as catching up on a movie with them.

#### References

Paul Wanjohi	Eng. Duncan Ndeda	Prasad Natraj

Director Principal Engineer General Manager

Edge Point Engineering Ministry of Petroleum AAF Middle East

+254720284146 +254722652283 +971505534812

Nelphat Mogare Rhoda Kanini

Director Director

Globtech Consultants Justinair Tech Ltd

+254720335578 +254721378362